<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="995">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 07, 2017</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01202994</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>43306</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01202994</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Practice Effects and Amyloid Imaging Using 18F-PIB or Flutemetamol PET and FDG-PET</brief_title>
  <official_title>Practice Effects and Amyloid Imaging Using 18F-PIB (18F-39-F-6-OH-BTA1) Known as [18FGE067]) or Flutemetamol PET and FDG-PET</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Alzheimer's disease (AD) is the most common cause of progressive cognitive decline in the
      United States. AD is characterized by severe impairments in learning, memory and other
      cognitive abilities that significantly interfere with daily functioning. The neuropathologic
      hallmarks of AD consist of neuritic plaques, neurofibrillary tangles, and selective neuronal
      cell loss. Amyloid plaques, which contain Abeta protein, are believed to play an integral
      role in the development of AD. Elevated levels of Abeta in the brain are also correlated with
      cognitive decline.

      Alzheimer's (AD) develops insidiously, making it difficult to identify early, yet treatment
      is most effective when begun during the early stages of the disease. Thus, it has become
      important for researchers to identify markers of early AD. This project will examine the
      relationship between four potential markers that may indicate the early development of AD:

        1. Mild cognitive impairment (MCI)or normal cognition

        2. Practice effects

        3. Amyloid plaque binding on 18F-PIB PET

        4. Glucose hypometabolism on FDG PET

      This project will recruit 25 subjects from an ongoing community-based study of memory and
      practice effects in cognitively normal, community-dwelling individuals who are age 65 and
      over (NIA #5K23AG028417-05). Each subject will undergo positron emission tomography (PET)
      with both 18F-Flutemetamol and FDG.

      The overall objective of this companion project is to study the biodistribution and binding
      of 18F-Flutemetamol in these subjects using PET imaging, which will provide biological
      evidence to support the overall hypothesis that failure to benefit from practice on a
      learning paradigm is an early marker of AD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overall objective of this companion study project is to study the biodistribution and
      binding of 18F-Flutemetamol using PET imaging in community-dwelling functionally intact
      elderly subjects. Understanding the biodistribution and binding of this radiopharmaceutical
      in normal patients with various levels of potential for cognitive decline will help determine
      its appropriate role as a disease biomarker and aid in the interpretation of images produced
      with this agent. Comparison with FDG-PET is essential to correlate metabolic changes and for
      anatomic co-registration of 18F-PIB images necessary for group analysis.

      We will use 18F-Flutemetamol and FDG-PET to compare subjects with low and high practice
      effects with the following aims and hypotheses:

      Specific Aim 1: Examine the relationship between practice effects and amyloid burden in a
      community sample.

      Specific Aim 2: Determine whether FDG-PET or 18F-Flutemetamol better distinguish individuals
      with high and low practice effects.

      Hypothesis 1: Practice effects will be negatively correlated with amyloid deposition, so that
      higher levels of practice effects (i.e., better repeat testing) will be associated with lower
      levels of brain amyloid deposition and lower levels of practice effects (i.e., poorer repeat
      testing) will be associated with greater levels of brain amyloid and these two groups are
      more clearly distinguishable with 18F-PIB than FDG-PET.

      Hypothesis 2: Patients with increased amyloid deposition shown with 18F-PIB will have an
      FDG-PET scan with more pronounced temporal and parietal hypometabolism as noted on visual
      review of images and on statistical image analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Practice effects and FDG-PET perfusion will be correlated with amyloid deposition in 18F-PIB.</measure>
    <time_frame>All measures will be collected within six month.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">27</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>18F-Flutemetamol</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects will undergo a PET scan with 18F-PIB, within six months of also undergoing an FDG-PET scan (PET scans will occur on separate days).
For the 18F-PIB PET scan: Approximately 185 MBq (5 mCi) of 18F-PIB will be injected intravenously and PET data collected for each subject.
The FDG-PET scan will follow the same procedures as routine scans obtained in a clinical setting (approximately 370 MBq of 18F-FDG will be injected intravenously and PET data collected for each subject). FDG-PET data will be used to correlate metabolic changes and for anatomic co-registration of 18F-PIB images.</description>
    <other_name>18F-39-F-6-OH-BTA1</other_name>
    <other_name>[18FGE067]</other_name>
    <other_name>Flutametamol PET</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must be currently enrolled in an NIA-sponsored, community-based study of
             practice effects in non-demented adults age 65 and older living independently (NIA
             #5K23AG028417-05)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of neurological disease known to affect cognition (e.g., stroke, head injury
             with loss of consciousness of &gt;30 minutes, seizure disorder, demyelinating disorder,
             mental retardation, etc.)

          -  Dementia based on DSM-IV criteria

          -  Current or past major psychiatric illness (e.g., schizophrenia, bipolar affective
             disorder)

          -  30-item Geriatric Depression Score &gt;14

          -  Evidence of stroke or mass lesion on CT or MRI scan

          -  History of alcoholism or other substance abuse

          -  Current use of cholinesterase inhibitors, other cognitive enhancers, antipsychotics,
             or anticonvulsant medications

          -  History of radiation therapy to the brain

          -  History of significant major medical illnesses, such as cancer or AIDS

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes or blood glucose &gt;180 mg/dl on the day of the FDG-PET scan

          -  Currently pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin Duff, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Utah</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah Center for Alzheimer's Care, Imaging and Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.utahmemory.org</url>
    <description>Link to the University of Utah Center for Alzheimer's Care, Imaging and Research</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- Old date names will be dropped in a few months (sometime in 2018)                        -->
  <lastchanged_date>March 20, 2017</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 14, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <!-- New date names                                                                           -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 16, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <!-- End of dates                                                                             -->
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Utah</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kevin Duff</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Phd</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Mild cognitive impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>PET</keyword>
  <keyword>Practice effects</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

